Guide to the International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry, Local 644 Records WAG.067
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry, Local 644 Records
1926-1981
1946-1975
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry
WAG.067
25.25 Linear Feet in 22 record cartons, 6 manuscript boxes, and 1 half manuscript box.
International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry, Local 644, was chartered by the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees in 1926 in response to theatrical and newsreel cameramen's dissatisfaction with their working conditions. The original charter gave Local 644 jurisdiction over all cameramen in the United States, after which additional local unions were established in California and Chicago. Local 644's cameramen have worked in television news, commercials, feature films, and the Army Signal Corps. This collection includes minutes of executive board and general meetings, correspondence files, contracts, and legal files concerning motion picture feature production, documentary film photographs, newsreel photographers, broadcast news photographers, and the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees East Coast Council.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry Local 644 was chartered by the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees (IATSE) on November 15, 1926. It conducted its meetings in the rooms of the United Scenic Artists and benefitted from the organization of studio mechanics in 1924. Chartering members were Eastern seaboard theatrical and newsreel cameramen dissatisfied with their working conditions characterized by long hours at the whim of producers. Activists who served as the interim president and first president of the local were Bill Miller and Billy Bitzer, cameraman for D.W. Griffith.
The original charter gave Local 644 jurisdiction over all cameramen in the U.S. In 1928 a sister local (659) was formed in California and in 1929 a third local (666) was established in Chicago, following the migration of the industry westward. Canadian jurisdiction was ceded to Toronto-based Local 667 in 1981.
In the twenties and thirties, the craft represented fewer than 100 people, and included both members of 2-men camera crews of the day: the director of photography and assistant camera operator. New York employers in the newsreel sector included Pathe (RKO, later Warner), Universal, Paramount, Fox Movie Tone, and MGM News of the Day (Hearst Metro Tone). Theatrical employers included the Astoria, Metropolitan, First National (Vitaphone), Fox (54th Street), Edison, and Biograph (Bronx) studios. Few of the studios survived the Depression and the loss of feature work to the West Coast.
During World War II Local 644 supplied combat cameramen and Army Signal Corpsmen. The Astoria Studios housed the Army Signal Corps between 1942 and 1972. As television networks grew, Local 644's newsreel cameramen found employment filming television news, a mainstay of the Local until the mid-1970s. Local 644 members also found work doing industrials and commercials. In the early 1950s and 1960s about 85 per cent of television commercials were produced in New York as well as situation comedies and other programming. Much of this work also migrated to Hollywood and in the 1970s and 1980s, increasingly work has moved "offshore" to Canada and the "diaspora" seeking more studio space and lower pay scales. As electronic news gathering replaced filmed network news in the mid-1970s, other unions secured jurisdiction at CBS, ABC and NBC. In the words of one network executive Local 644's film newsreel cameramen were "dinosaurs" in a changing industry. They were forced to join NABET or the IBEW, or retire.
Through the 1980s, feature film work in New York City and on the East Coast increased dramatically, offsetting the loss of commercial work and newsreel jurisdiction. In 1990 NABET Local 15 merged with IATSE, increasing Local 644's membership from 700 to 1,200 members. The Motion Picture Screen Cartoonists Local 841 merged with Local 644 in 1988. The recent revival in computer animation and graphics has led the Local to organize in these fields. In 1990, Local 644 signed the first-ever "below the line" pact with Mexico, Argentina and Brazil. This resulted in the first joint Mexican-American strike in the Mayan jungles against an Italian producer. Local 644 was also the first local to inaugurate marketing ventures with New York City and New York State in the European market bringing over $10 million in new business to date. With Local 644's leadership, IATSE gave the East Coast Council jurisdiction over all feature films on the East Coast with budgets under $6 million (low-budget films). The 1991-2 boycott of New York by major producers stressed the importance of low-budget productions to the industry and resulted in modifications of work rules. As of 1994, the Council managed over $100 million worth of low-budget contracts.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Meeting minutes from 1926-1983 are available on microfilm; call number is R-7446.
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection include minutes from various committee meetings, executive board meetings, and general meetings; correspondence files; contracts and agreements; and legal files concerning motion picture feature production, documentary film photographs, newsreel photographers, broadcast news photographers, and the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees East Coast Council. Additional materials found throughout the collection includes newspaper clippings, newsletters, some photographic prints, elections and nominations materials, research files, financial documents, weekly reports, promotional materials, and legislative booklets.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees, Local 644, in 1989. The accession number associated with this gift is 1989.008.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Theaters -- United States -- Employees; Motion picture industry -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Television broadcasting -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Collective labor agreements -- Motion picture industry -- United States.; Television camera operators.; Motion picture industry; Collective bargaining -- New York (State); Briefs (legal documents); International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industry
- Correspondence A-C, 1947-1975 (Box 1)
- Correspondence C-H, 1948-1973 (Box 2)
- Correspondence I-M, 1927-1971 (Box 3)
- Correspondence M-N, 1928-1972 (Box 4)
- Correspondence N-S, 1927-1974 (Box 5)
- Correspondence S-V, 1927-1971 (Box 6)
- Correspondence V-W, 1929-1972 (Box 7)
- General Files A-C, 1954-1978 (Box 7)
- General Files C-M, 1947-1975 (Box 8)
- General Files M-P, 1959-1975 (Box 9)
- General Files P-W, 1935-1976 (Box 10)
- IATSE Legal Files C-L, 1964-1978 (Box 11, Box 24, Box 25)
- IATSE Legal Files M-N, 1958-1978 (Box 12)
- IATSE Legal Files V-W, 1960-1977 (Box 14, Box 26, Box 27)
- IATSE Legal Files W, 1967-1977 (Box 15)
- Old Contracts A-C, 1960-1976 (Box 15)
- Old Contracts C-H, 1948-1975 (Box 16)
- Old Contracts I-M, 1952-1973 (Box 17)
- Old Contracts M-N, 1952-1973 (Box 18)
- Old Contracts P-W, 1936-1976 (Box 19)
- Old Feature and Commercial Files H-M, 1954-1977 (Box 20)
- Old Feature and Commercial Files M-Q, 1956-1977 (Box 21, Box 28)
- Old Membership Applications A-E, 1926-1981 (Box 22)
- Old Membership Applications F-W, 1926-1981 (Box 23, Box 29)